

Ruben Roque Dias

@ ruben.roque.dias@gmail.com

+351 915 555 909

rubenroquedias

https://www.linkedin.com/in/rubenroquedias

25th of September, 1993

🔒 Vila Nova de Gaia, Portugal

Profile

I hold a master's degree in Electrical and Computers Engineering since 2017. I am currently a Simulation Developer and Consultant with 1.5 years of experience, specialising in discrete-event simulation. Previously, I worked for half a year as a front-end developer, mainly using vanilla Javascript, jQuery, and the KendoUl framework. I was also a Teaching Assistant for one semester during my master's degree.

I am an efficient and versatile engineer. Working in a team environment and having direct contact with clients has made me an effective communicator and a proactive team member. I am a fast learner, and always eager to increase and share my knowledge.

Work Experience

January 2019 -Present

Simulation Developer & Consultant

@ INESC TEC, Porto, Portugal

- · Leading Simulation projects for improving operational results and KPIs of manufacturing companies
- · Developing virtual factory models using discrete event simulation (Simio software)
- Leveraging Simio's API using C# for enhanced connectivity with 3rd party software
- · Performing analysis using Excel and Java
- · Training new colleagues that come to research/work in this area, and guiding masters students during their thesis

April 2018 -December 2018

Front-End Developer

@ Dreamo - Balanced Work Systems, Matosinhos, Portugal

- · Developing interfaces for managing workflows and communication
- · Creating back-end services and database structures to support the functionalities being developed
- · Working with vanilla Javascript, jQuery, C#, KendoUI, SQL Server and of course, HTML and CSS
- · Developed mobile app prototypes for managing communication & notifications using Ionic and PhoneGap

March 2017 -March 2018

Simulation Developer & Researcher

@ INESC TEC, Porto, Portugal

- Developing virtual factory models using discrete event simulation (Simio software), to improve operational performance of manufacturing companies
- · Leveraging Simio's API using C#
- Performing analysis using Excel and Java
- Researching within European H2020 projects, ScalABLE and FASTEN, on real-life simulation applications to leverage the emergence of Industry 4.0

September 2015 -February 2016

Teaching Assistant

@ Faculty of Engineering of the University of Porto, Portugal

· Assisting in laboratory classes of the Digital Systems Laboratory course during my Master's

Education

September 2011 -March 2017

Master in Electrical and Computers Engineering

@ Faculty of Engineering of the University of Porto, Portugal

- My branch of study was Automation, thus I worked frequently with PLCs and MES softwares
- Gained knowledge on industrial/applied electronics, embedded systems and industrial informatics, often creating
 applications using microprocessors (e.g. Arduino)
- Specialised in Industrial Management, becoming knowledgeable on enterprise information systems, decision support systems and operations management

Master Thesis - Models for Improvement Management and Operational Performance @ INESC TEC, Porto, Portugal

- Explored Simulation as a tool in supporting decision making in the context of manufacturing industries
- Created a virtual factory model in AnyLogic to simulate a job-shop environment and test improvement strategies
- Used InfluxDB for real-time data storing to handle the data generated by the simulator
- · Provided real-time data visualisation using Grafana

September 2014 -March 2015

Erasmus+ Exchange Program

@ Wrocław University of Technology, Poland

· Gained knowledge regarding my specialisation (Industrial Management), and took classes on Polish Language

Personal Interests

iOS Development (using Swift and Xcode)

I am a self-taught developer for iOS applications. I am currently developing a financial tracking app on my free time which allows me to explore and test what I have learned. I have completed a full course from Udemy to get started, as well as some others taught by highly regarded Youtube instructors, such as a few of the paid courses offered by Brian Voong from Let's Build that App, a well known professional instructor and developer in the Swift community.

Hobbies

Technology, music, playing football with friends, fitness, traveling.

Software Skills

Programming Skills

Experienced Basic Advanced **Basic** • Swift · Simio FlexSim Java · AnyLogic · Visual Components Javascript • C# · MS Excel · PLC Next · HTML / CSS Python · MS PowerPoint Grafana jQuery · Assembly MS Word InfluxDB · SQL · Visual Basic • C

Complementary Education and Training

February 2019	OPC-UA / PLC Next Workshop
	@ INESC TEC, Porto, Portugal

January 2019 FlexSim Workshop

@ INESC TEC, Porto, Portugal

March 2017 Visual Components Workshop

@ INESC TEC, Porto, Portugal

May 2015 Public Speaking Techniques

@ BEST group, Faculty of Engineering of the University of Porto, Portugal

Scientific Conferences

September 2017 Presenter - A Simulation and Optimisation Framework for Integrated Planning and

Process Design

@ ENEGI 2017, Porto, Portugal

June 2017 Presenter - Models for Improvement Management and Operational Performance

@ IO 2017, Valença, Portugal

Languages

Portuguese • native language

English • fluent

German • basic